You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Parkinson’s is one of the fastest growing
neurological conditions in the world
and though there is currently
no cure for the disease,
there are dietary changes
that can significantly improve
symptoms of the disease.
And we start today with the
potential benefits of coffee.
When James Parkinson first described
the classical symptoms of the disease,
he could hardly foresee the
evolution of our understanding
over the next two hundred years
like the role of nutrition,
increasing Parkinson's disease
risk with high dietary intakes
of animal fat, iron, mercury,
and dairy products,
whereas the intake of antioxidants
and a plant-based dietary pattern
may be protective.
Plant-based diets are known
to preserve body tissues
from oxidative stress and
inflammation, both hallmarks
of chronic degenerative
diseases like Parkinson's.
On the contrary, animal-based foods,
particularly rich in animal
proteins and saturated fats,
are correlated with the promotion
of neurodegenerative diseases,
in addition to some
of the leading killers
like cancer, heart
disease, diabetes, etc.
Not all plants are necessarily
good though. For example,
the potential neurotoxicity
of graviola,
a fruit known as soursop.
Consumption of soursop can lower
blood pressure and uric acid levels
but may also cause an atypical
form of Parkinson's disease,
because the fruit contains
neurotoxic compounds.
And indeed, population studies
do show a link between
the overconsumption of soursop
with neurodegenerative disease.
Yes, those who follow a predominantly
plant-based diet may show
the lowest prevalence and incidence
of Parkinson's disease,
but plant-based nutrition is
not just about reducing the risk
but can be used to
manage the disease.
In my video, "Treating
Parkinson's Disease with Diet,"
I discussed this case report,
in which a diet low in animal fat
and including both
whole grains every day,
as well as one to two cups
of strawberries a day,
seemed to be effective in reducing
symptoms of Parkinson's disease.
But there are like 20,000
edible plants out there,
and only a limited number
of them have been studied
for anti-Parkinson's activity.
One plant that's gotten a lot
of attention is coffee,
which may exert a
protective effect against
the development of
Parkinson's disease
and may even help slow down
the progression of the disease,
based on studies like this.
They show the Parkinson's patients
who drink coffee or caffeinated tea
appear to cut their risk
of dying prematurely in half.
But correlation
doesn't mean causation.
You don't know if caffeine really
works until you...put it to the test.
Caffeine for the treatment
of Parkinson's disease.
A six-week randomized placebo-
controlled double-blind study.
The caffeine group was started out
at approximately a cup of coffee's
worth of caffeine twice a day, once
in the morning and once after lunch,
and then increasing it to two cups'
worth twice a day, which would
be like four cups of black tea
twice a day or six cups of green.
And a significant improvement
in Parkinson's symptoms
within three weeks
compared to placebo.
A cheap, safe, simple
treatment for Parkinson's,
though an important limitation
was the duration of the study.
Caffeine has what's called
a tachyphylactic property,
meaning its effects tend to diminish
over time with repeated use
(at least when trying
to combat sleepiness).
So it would be really nice
to see the study repeated
over a longer time frame. But
there was no such longer study
until five years later.
Randomizing Parkinson's patients
to about two cups of coffee worth
of caffeine twice a day for
not six weeks, but more than
six months, and no benefit
over placebo. Drats.
Caffeine did not provide sustained
symptomatic benefit after all.
So caffeine may have a short-term
benefit, which quickly dissipates.
Regardless, caffeine
cannot be recommended
as symptomatic therapy
for Parkinsonism.
In our next story,
we look at how low levels of
neurotoxic chemicals in cheese
may explain the connection
between dairy product consumption
and Parkinson’s disease.
Four things that we can do that may reduce
our risk of developing Parkinson's disease
is exercise, avoiding dairy products,
pesticides, and avoid getting hit in the head
(which means wearing your seatbelt,
bike helmet), and—
if you read journal articles written by
scientists
with way too much
time on their hands—
avoid getting attacked
by extraterrestrials,
a leading cause of traumatic brain injury
in comic books.
What about avoiding pesticides and other
industrial pollutants?
A recent autopsy study
found higher levels in
the brains of Parkinson's
victims of PCBs
found in Monsanto's Aroclor, which was
banned in 1979, but still pollutes the world.
And, the more PCBs found in the brain, the
worse the brain damage.
The worst three PCBs appeared to be
numbers 138, 153, and 180—
the levels of all of which are
significantly lower
in the bodies of those
eating plant-based diets.
So: "Does a vegan diet reduce risk [of]
Parkinson's disease?"
Good question.
Well, we know that every single prospective
study on dairy products
or milk and Parkinson's disease tended to
find increased risk.
It may be that "dairy
products in the United
States are contaminated
with neurotoxic chemicals".
There's substantial evidence
suggesting that
"exposure to pesticides may increase
Parkinson's disease risk,"
and autopsies found higher levels of pollutants
and pesticides
in the brains of Parkinson's
disease patients,
and some of these toxins are present at low
levels in dairy products.
They're talking about toxins like
tetrahydroisoquinoline,
a Parkinsonism-related compound found
predominantly in cheese.
Although the amounts of this neurotoxin—
even in cheese—are not really high,
the concern is that the chemical may
accumulate in the brain
over long periods
of consumption.
Finally today, we look at how
plant-based diets in general
may be used to successfully
treat Parkinson’s disease,
in part, by boosting
L-DOPA levels.
Caffeine consumption,
both in Asian and Western populations,
appears to protect against the
development of Parkinson’s disease.
But, what if you already have it?
A new study found that
giving folks the equivalent
of about two cups of coffee
a day worth of caffeine
significantly improved
symptoms of the disease.
Of course, there’s only so much
you can charge for coffee,
so drug companies took caffeine,
and added a side group
so they could patent it into new drugs,
which appear to work no better
than plain caffeine—
which is dramatically cheaper,
and probably safer.
Similarly, other plant foods,
such as berries, may be protective.
And, plant-based diets, in general,
may help prevent Parkinson’s.
Animal fat and dairy
may increase risk,
whereas “a plant-based diet
dietary pattern may protect against
[Parkinson’s disease].”
We don’t know if it’s the
animal fat per se, though;
it could be the animal protein
that’s increasing risk,
or maybe it’s the dairy,
the mercury in fish,
the blood-based heme iron,
or less of the protective antioxidants
in plant foods and
plant-based diets.
We didn’t know,
until recently.
There have been successful case
reports, like this one, in which a dietician
was struck down with Parkinson’s,
and she was able to clear most of her
symptoms with a plant-based diet
rich in strawberries, whole wheat,
and brown rice—rich sources
of these two phytonutrients.
But, there hasn’t been a formal
interventional trial published—until now.
At its root, Parkinson’s is a
dopamine-deficiency disease,
because of a die-off
of dopamine-generating cells
in the brain.
These cells make
dopamine from L-dopa,
derived from certain amino
acids in our diet.
But, just like we saw
with the serotonin story,
the consumption of animal protein
may block the transport of L-dopa
into the brain,
crowding it out.
So, at first, researchers tried what’s
called a “protein redistribution diet.”
Let’s basically only let people
eat meat for supper,
so that patients are hopefully sleeping
by the time the negative effects kick in.
But researchers didn’t consider cutting
out all animal products altogether,
until it was discovered
that fiber consumption
naturally boosts L-dopa levels.
So, hey, “a plant-based diet,
particularly in its vegan variant,
is expected to raise levodopa
bioavailability and bring some
advantages in the management
of [Parkinson’s] disease
through two mechanisms:
a reduced protein intake and
an increased fiber intake…”
That’s why plant protein works best,
because that’s where fiber is found.
So, they put people on
a strictly vegan diet,
keeping beans towards
the end of the day,
and indeed found a significant
improvement in symptoms.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.